May I be happy
Bolehkah kubahagia
May I be free from suffering
Bolehkah kubebas dari derita
May I be free from enmity
Bolehkah kubebas dari permusuhan
May I be free from obstacles and dangers
Bolehkah kubebas dari rintangan dan marabahaya
May I live in peace and happily
Bolehkah kuhidup damai dan bahagia
Maintain purity in body and speech
Jaga kesucian jasmani dan kata
Free from all suffering and danger
Bebas dari segala derita dan bahaya
What brought you up here? What have you done?
Kenapa kau ke sini? Apa yang telah kau lakukan?
RAMPA ISLAND, CHONBURI, 1976 CE
PULAU RAMPA, CHONBURI, 1976 MASEHI
Aim!
Aim!
How are you? Are you doing well?
Bagaimana kabarmu? Baik?
I haven't been here for a month, and missed you so much!
Sudah sebulan aku tak kemari, aku sangat merindukanmu!
Here,
Di sini,
everyone is responsible for their own.
semua bertanggung jawab atas diri sendiri.
I've got good news.
Aku membawa kabar baik.
Mother said I'll be released soon.
Kata Bunda, aku akan segera dibebaskan.
Really?
Sungguh?
They're working on the paperwork right now.
Mereka sedang mengurus surat-suratku.
So until then, you'll come and get me from here, right?
Nanti kau akan datang untuk menjemputku dari sini, bukan?
Go line up quickly.
Berbarislah.
Mother is coming down.
Bunda akan turun.
My name is Ms. Pritsana, I'm in charge here.
Namaku Bu Pritsana, penanggung jawab tempat ini.
Everyone here calls me "Mother."
Semua orang di sini memanggilku "Bunda."
Introduce yourself to your friends.
Perkenalkan diri ke teman-temanmu.
I'm Ingkhwan, from Darunphorn youth home.
Aku Ingkhwan, dari panti rehabilitasi remaja Darunphorn.
Ingkhwan,
Ingkhwan,
a true Northerner.
orang Utara sejati.
Silence! What's everyone laughing at? We're in front of Mother, remember.
Diam! Apa yang lucu? Ingat, kita sedang ada di hadapan Bunda.
We're on an island and it's just us here.
Kita ada di sebuah pulau dan hanya ada kita di sini.
It's essential to have rules.
Penting untuk memiliki aturan.
I would like each of you
Aku mau kalian semua
to assist Ingkhwan in becoming familiar with our regulations here.
membantu Ingkhwan mempelajari aturan kita di sini.
Please look after her, Aim-orn.
Tolong bantu dia, Aim-orn.
Yes, Mother.
Ya, Bunda.
Please take care of her, Maprang. I'll be back.
Tolong bantu dia, Maprang. Aku akan kembali.
Return to your work now!
Kembalilah bekerja!
Nuch,
Nuch,
take the new student to the building.
bawa siswa baru itu ke gedung.
PINITKHUN REFORMATORY SCHOOL AREA FOR YOUTH CIVIC DEVELOPMENT
SEKOLAH PEMBINAAN PINITKHUN TEMPAT PENGEMBANGAN KEWARGAAN REMAJA
We don't have a backup small boat here like you might think.
Di sini tak ada kapal kecil cadangan seperti yang kau duga.
I'm happy to Mother with anything.
Aku bersedia membantu Bunda dalam apa pun.
Just give me some food and a place to sleep, and I'm good.
Beri saja aku makanan dan tempat untuk tidur, sudah cukup.
As for the radio I asked you to get repaired last time,
Radio yang kuminta kau perbaiki,
you couldn't handle fixing that.
kau tak bisa menanganinya.
Yet you're asking to stay.
Tapi, kau minta untuk tinggal di sini.
If an emergency comes up,
Jika terjadi keadaan darurat,
it'll be a problem for everyone.
akan jadi masalah untuk semua orang.
The next boat won't come until the storm is over.
Kapal berikutnya tak akan datang sampai badai reda.
In the meantime, you can stay at the lighthouse.
Sambil menunggu, kau boleh tinggal di mercusuar.
Thank you, Mother.
Terima kasih, Bunda.
Come in.
Masuk.
You two can leave now.
Kalian berdua boleh pergi.
"Miss Ingkhwan Pornraksa,
"Nona Ingkhwan Pornraksa,
age 17, sent here due to…"
usia 17, dikirim kemari karena…"
I do not care what you have done before.
Aku tak peduli apa yang telah kau lakukan.
At this school,
Di sekolah ini,
we're ready to give everyone a chance to turn their life around.
kami siap memberi semua orang kesempatan mengubah hidup.
You want a fresh start, don't you?
Kau mau awal yang baru, bukan?
The government closed a secret island prison
Pemerintahan menutup penjara rahasia di pulau
Mystery on island: Dozens of prisoners found dead.
Misteri di pulau: Puluhan napi ditemukan tewas.
The Interior Minister plans to convert the prison
Kementerian Dalam Negeri mau mengubah penjara itu
into a reformer school for young female offenders.
menjadi sekolah pengembangan untuk perempuan muda terpidana.
PINITKHUN REFORMATORY SCHOOL
SEKOLAH PEMBINAAN PINITKHUN
THE GUARDIAN ANGEL OF PINITKHUN SCHOOL
MALAIKAT PELINDUNG SEKOLAH PINITKHUN
Your job is now to light the dorm lantern every evening.
Sekarang tugasmu menyalakan lentera asrama setiap malam.
Refill the water every day.
Isi ulang air setiap hari.
Everyone here must wake up before sunrise,
Semua di sini harus bangun sebelum fajar,
attend classes on time,
hadir di kelas tepat waktu,
and be in the dormitory by 7:00 p.m. sharp.
dan kembali ke asrama tepat pukul 19.00.
If you want to push the rules, be my guest.
Jika mau melanggar aturan, silakan saja.
Wish the dorm had electricity instead of lanterns.
Andai asrama ini memakai listrik, bukan lentera.
I'm jealous of Mother's room with it's proper lamp.
Aku iri dengan kamar Bunda yang memiliki lampu.
If you don't like it, feel free to sleep on the floor.
Jika kau tak suka, silakan tidur di lantai saja.
No one's stopping you.
Tak ada yang melarang.
But since you're alone,
Namun, karena sendirian,
you'd better watch out.
sebaiknya kau waspada.
Especially at night.
Terutama pada malam hari.
Who's there?
Ada siapa di sana?
Don't forget to wash it, it's filthy!
Jangan lupa dicuci, itu kotor sekali!
Isn't this too much?
Tidakkah ini keterlaluan?
This filthy bitch's job now? Shoveling shit for you now.
Tugas si jalang jorok ini sekarang? Menyerok kotoran untukmu.
Every plate of rice and every bit of food,
Setiap piring nasi dan setiap sisa makanan,
don't waste it, they're precious.
jangan dibuang, semuanya berharga.
Many people are starving.
Banyak orang yang kelaparan.
Always remember all the starving children.
Selalu ingat semua anak-anak kelaparan.
When you're making a garland,
Saat membuat rangkaian bunga,
you must take care with each flower.
setiap bunga harus kalian kerjakan dengan hati-hati.
Just one out of place,
Satu saja yang tak sesuai,
the whole garland won't look right.
seluruh karangan akan tampak aneh.
Come on, I'll help.
Ayo, biar kubantu.
If you can't handle it, why not ask for help?
Jika tak bisa, kenapa tak minta tolong?
When you have time, stop by the infirmary.
Begitu kau sempat, mampirlah ke klinik.
Put some antiseptic on your wound.
Oleskan antiseptik pada lukamu.
If something is bothering you, feel free to tell me.
Jika ada yang mengganjal, jangan segan memberi tahu aku.
Just think me of as one of your friends.
Anggap saja aku salah satu temanmu.
I'm here for you.
Aku ada untukmu.
So have you seen the ghost?
Apa kau sudah lihat hantu itu?
Who's there?
Ada siapa di sana?
Enough with the pranks!
Berhentilah mengerjaiku!
I'm not scared!
Aku tidak takut!
Next time, you'll be finished.
Lain kali, kau akan mati.
Carving…
Mengukir…
is a craft that requires focus and precision.
adalah kerajinan yang memerlukan fokus dan presisi.
Because it can transform something ordinary or unattractive
Karena bisa mengubah sesuatu yang biasa atau tidak menarik
into something beautiful.
menjadi indah.
What happened last night?
Apa yang terjadi semalam?
Nothing, Mother.
Tidak ada, Bunda.
Will you take care of this or must I enforce order myself?
Kau akan membereskan ini atau aturan harus kutegakkan sendiri?
Last night, it was you!
Semalam, itu kau!
What?
Apa?
Don't play innocent.
Jangan berlagak polos.
You're the one who pushed Aim down the stairs.
Kau yang mendorong Aim di tangga.
Admit it! We won't tell Mother.
Mengakulah! Kami tak akan memberi tahu Bunda.
I didn't do it.
Bukan aku pelakunya.
Just admit you did it.
Akui saja kau pelakunya.
Let go of me.
Lepaskan aku.
You saw that, right? She's the one who did it.
Kalian lihat, bukan? Dialah pelakunya.
But…
Namun…
I didn't see Ing do anything.
aku tak melihat Ing melakukan apa pun.
Of course you'll take her side. You're both country bumpkins.
Tentu saja kau memihaknya. Kalian sama-sama kampungan.
If you don't own up, everyone else will take the fall.
Kalau kau tak mau mengaku, semua orang akan disalahkan.
But honestly, I didn't do it.
Jujur, bukan aku pelakunya.
No meal for you all tonight.
Tak ada makanan untuk malam ini.
Get back to work now.
Kembalilah bekerja.
Make more excuses and they will be punished because of you.
Jika beralasan lagi, mereka akan dihukum karena kau.
I'm sorry that I was a coward.
Maaf aku bersikap pengecut.
You can be mad at me.
Kau boleh marah kepadaku.
But I believe you didn't hurt Maprang.
Namun, aku percaya kau tidak menyakiti Maprang.
Aim said you're a bumpkin.
Aim menyebutmu kampungan.
Are you from the North too?
Apa kau berasal dari Utara juga?
Yes.
Ya.
I'm Ploy.
Aku Ploy.
I thought you wouldn't talk to me.
Kukira kau tak mau bicara denganku.
You always keep to yourself.
Kau selalu menyendiri.
This is how it is here.
Di sini memang seperti itu.
Those who have been here longer like Aim
Yang sudah lebih lama di sini seperti Aim
always bully the newcomers.
selalu merundung pendatang baru
and Mother allows it.
dan Bunda membiarkannya.
But we all think the same,
Namun, pikiran kami semua sama,
that if we keep our heads down,
jika kami tetap merunduk,
at least we'll have a place to stay.
setidaknya akan punya tempat tinggal.
As you know,
Kau sudah tahu,
the girls don't have a home to go back to.
gadis-gadis ini tak punya rumah.
Aim, what brings you here?
Aim, kenapa kau kemari?
When you picked up the new girl, did you talk to her?
Saat menjemput gadis baru itu, apa kau bicara dengannya?
I asked for her name and where she's from.
Aku menanyakan nama dan asalnya.
What did she say?
Apa katanya?
Nothing.
Tidak ada.
On the mainland,
Di daratan utama,
have you heard of Darunphorn Home?
kau pernah dengar tentang Panti Darunphorn?
Darunphorn Home?
Panti Darunphorn?
Yes.
Ya.
It's an orphanage.
Itu sebuah panti asuhan.
I saw in the news. It got closed down all of a sudden.
Aku lihat di berita. Panti itu tiba-tiba ditutup.
Introduce yourself.
Perkenalkan dirimu.
- Country bumpkin!
- Kampungan!
Strip her.
Telanjangi dia.
No.
Tidak.
What is it?
Ada apa?
You, come here.
Kemari kau.
What?
Apa?
Let go.
Lepaskan.
- Let go of me. - Stop squirming.
- Lepaskan aku. - Berhenti bergerak.
A stupid bumpkin like you never learns their lesson!
Orang kampung bodoh sepertimu tak pernah bisa belajar!
Please don't hurt me.
Jangan sakiti aku.
I'm begging you.
Kumohon.
No.
Tidak.
There's still some shit here.
Masih ada kotoran di sini.
No!
Tidak!
Aim, what's wrong?
Aim, ada apa?
What happened?
Apa yang terjadi?
You saw it, right?
Kalian lihat, 'kan?
What?
Apa?
An old woman.
Ada wanita tua.
Is it…
Apa itu…
a ghost?
hantu?
Nonsense, Nuch.
Bukan, Nuch.
Don't scare her.
Jangan buat dia takut.
She looks pale now.
Sekarang dia pucat.
What happened, Aim?
Apa yang terjadi, Aim?
Did someone hurt you?
Ada yang menyakitimu?
Are you gonna say it?
Kau akan mengatakannya?
Let go of me.
Lepaskan aku.
Say it!
Katakan!
Okay.
Baiklah.
Now, say it.
Katakan.
You know something
Kau tahu sesuatu
I don't know, don't you?
yang tak kuketahui.
I…
Aku…
I think that ghost has something to do with Ing.
Sepertinya hantu itu ada kaitannya dengan Ing.
How?
Bagaimana?
I don't follow.
Aku tak paham.
Something happened to me after I dumped shit on her,
Sesuatu terjadi kepadaku setelah menumpahkan kotoran ke dirinya,
you know that?
kau tahu?
Have you all
Apa kalian
heard of "a godmother ghost"?
pernah dengar "hantu ibu baptis"?
When I was young, my grandma told me that
Saat masih kecil, nenekku bilang
everyone is born, molded by spirits.
semua orang lahir, dibentuk oleh roh.
Most northern people believe
Kebanyakan orang utara percaya
a newborn is guarded by a ghost
bayi yang baru lahir dijaga oleh hantu
as if it were another mother.
seakan-akan dia ibu kedua.
So, the newborn
Jadi, bayi itu
is like a human's and a ghost's child.
seperti anak manusia dan hantu.
So, we have a ritual to buy it off from the ghost.
Jadi, ada ritual untuk membelinya dari hantu.
A ghost's child for three days, a human's child for four days.
Anak hantu selama tiga hari dan anak manusia selama empat hari.
Whoever this child belongs to, come to take it.
Siapa pun yang memiliki anak ini, ambillah.
Come! Take it and raise it!
Datang! Ambil dan rawat dia!
I'd like to buy off this child.
Aku mau membeli anak ini.
The baby belongs to human now.
Kini, bayi itu milik manusia.
No ghost can disturb her.
Tak ada hantu yang bisa mengganggunya.
No ghost can take her.
Tak ada hantu yang bisa mengambilnya.
Keep this doll's head
Kepala boneka ini
with your child all the time
harus selalu bersama anakmu
until she's mature.
sampai dia dewasa.
Don't mess around.
Jangan main-main.
Do it properly,
Semua harus benar
or bad things may happen.
jika tak ingin sial.
Keep that in mind.
Ingat itu.
Any child that has never been in that ritual
Anak yang tak pernah menjalani ritual itu
will be taken by the ghost
akan diambil hantu
or it may stay with her.
atau akan tetap bersama dia.
What haunted us is her godmother ghost?
Yang menghantui kita adalah hantu ibu baptisnya?
Sounds like just a folk tale.
Itu cuma cerita rakyat.
Interesting.
Menarik.
I just don't buy it.
Namun, aku tak percaya.
Who's there?
Siapa di sana?
- Help! - Quiet.
- Tolong! - Diam.
Help!
Diam!
- Help! - Shut up. Be quiet now.
- Tolong! - Tutup mulut. Diamlah.
Help!
Tolong!
- Help! - Be quiet.
- Tolong! - Diam.
What's all the noise?
Kenapa berisik sekali?
I heard you're quite competent.
Kudengar kau cukup kompeten.
Prove it to me.
Buktikanlah kepadaku.
Look at you.
Lihat dirimu.
What can you do to me in this state?
Bisa lakukan apa padaku di kondisi ini?
Let me go!
Lepaskan aku!
Please!
Kumohon!
You're squirming just like a worm.
Kau menggeliat seperti cacing.
You worthless scum.
Dasar sampah.
Let me go!
Lepaskan aku!
I forgot you're filthier than shit.
Aku lupa kau lebih kotor dari tahi.
Let me wipe my feet.
Biar kulap kakiku.
Get off of me!
Lepaskan aku!
Are you angry?
Apa kau marah?
Why? You're mad at me?
Kenapa? Kau marah kepadaku?
So mad that you want to kill me?
Begitu marah sampai mau membunuhku?
Go on. Kill me.
Silakan. Bunuh aku.
Let me go.
Lepaskan aku.
Please.
Kumohon.
Keep your damn mouth shut about this.
Tutup mulutmu tentang ini.
If anyone finds out,
Jika ada yang tahu,
they'll suffer the same fate.
nasib mereka akan sama.
Can you take me out of here, Pin?
Bisa bawa aku pergi dari sini, Pin?
I don't want to be here.
Aku tak mau ada di sini.
Why not?
Kenapa?
I just want to start my life over.
Aku cuma mau hidup dari awal lagi.
I really can't help you.
Aku tak bisa membantumu.
I can't even find a way to contact the mainland.
Aku bahkan tak bisa cari cara menghubungi daratan utama.
Please.
Kumohon.
No one else can help me.
Cuma kau yang bisa membantu.
I'm sorry, Ing.
Maaf, Ing.
You should leave
Sebaiknya kau pergi
before someone sees you here. You'll be punished.
sebelum ketahuan. Kau akan dihukum.
This is for the rain.
Agar tak kehujanan.
The reason you're here is to learn to be a better person.
Alasanmu ada di sini adalah untuk belajar jadi orang yang lebih baik.
It's not to behave like whore, chasing after a guy.
Bukan bertingkah seperti pelacur, mengejar lelaki.
Keep in mind,
Ingat,
if you still behave like you used to,
jika masih bersikap seperti dulu,
if you still misbehave,
jika masih nakal,
don't expect any leniency from me or that I will let you leave this place.
jangan harap aku bersikap lunak atau membiarkan kalian pergi dari sini.
Worthless scum like you
Sampah seperti kalian
won't be accepted by the society.
tak akan diterima masyarakat.
No, let go!
Tidak, lepaskan!
Mother.
Bunda.
It's me, Aim. It's me, Mother.
Ini aku, Aim. Ini aku, Bunda.
It's Aim.
Ini Aim.
What happened, Mother?
Ada apa, Bunda?
What happened to you?
Bunda kenapa?
Ing.
Ing.
Could you walk with me to the bathroom?
Bisa ikut aku ke kamar mandi?
If she has been in the ritual,
Jika dia sudah menjalani ritual,
she should have a doll's head.
seharusnya punya kepala boneka.
But if she hasn't…
Namun, jika belum…
Actually, I want to talk to you.
Sebetulnya, aku mau bicara denganmu.
Go on.
Bicaralah.
Aim thought I can talk to you.
Menurut Aim, aku bisa bicara denganmu.
So, she forced me to tell your story.
Jadi, dia memaksaku untuk menceritakan kisahmu.
About what?
Tentang apa?
About your godmother ghost.
Tentang hantu ibu baptismu.
If we find it, what would we do?
Jika kita menemukannya, harus bagaimana?
Let's find it first. She might not have a doll's head.
Cari saja dahulu. Mungkin dia tak punya kepala boneka.
And what do they think?
Lalu, apa pendapat mereka?
they don't buy it.
Mereka sangsi.
She thinks you did all that.
Dia pikir kau yang melakukan semuanya.
As long as you're here,
Selama kau ada di sini,
they'll keep giving you trouble.
mereka akan terus menyulitkanmu.
What does it mean, Aim?
Apa artinya, Aim?
Ploy has only the head.
Ploy cuma punya kepala.
Leave.
Pergi.
What's going on?
Ada apa?
Say it.
Katakan.
Ing has been missing since this morning.
Ing hilang sejak tadi pagi.
Ing.
Ing.
Are you here?
Kau ada di sini?
Where are you, Ingkhwan?
Kau di mana, Ingkhwan?
- Ingkhwan.
- Ingkhwan.
Where are you?
Kau di mana?
Ingkhwan, where are you?
Ingkhwan,kau di mana?
Hiding here and not caring about anything.
Bersembunyi di sini, tak acuh.
What are you plotting, bumpkin?
Sedang merencanakan apa, Kampungan?
I just want to be alone.
Aku cuma mau sendiri.
Please leave me alone.
Tolong biarkan aku sendiri.
You want to be alone?
Kau mau sendiri?
What are you doing? Let go.
Apa yang kau lakukan? Lepaskan.
We're helping you.
Kami membantumu.
Let go.
Lepaskan.
- You want to be alone, right? - Let go.
- Kau mau sendiri, bukan? - Lepaskan.
Let me go.
Lepaskan aku.
Let go.
Lepas.
Shut up.
Diam.
Let me go. I'm begging you.
Lepaskan aku. Kumohon.
Please!
Kumohon!
Shut up.
Diam.
Let go!
Lepaskan!
Please don't hurt me.
Jangan sakiti aku.
Since you want to be alone,
Karena kau mau sendiri,
try to stay here overnight.
menginap saja di sini.
But if you want out,
Kalau mau keluar,
try calling your ghost mom for help.
coba panggil ibu hantumu untuk membantu.
Don't!
Jangan!
- Ingkhwan. - Can you hear me?
- Ingkhwan. - Bisa dengar aku?
Aim. What if what Ploy said is true?
Aim. Bagaimana kalau yang Ploy katakan benar?
The godmother ghost.
Hantu ibu baptis.
Hey, Ploy.
Hei, Ploy.
Guys, Ploy fainted.
Ploy pingsan.
Ploy!
Ploy!
What's going on?
Ada apa?
Don't say anything. I'll handle this.
Jangan katakan apa pun. Biar kutangani.
It's just Ingkhwan ran away.
Masalahnya, Ingkhwan kabur.
So I asked them to find her.
Kuminta mereka mencarinya.
Since when?
Sejak kapan?
We don't know.
Kami tak tahu.
If she could get away,
Jika dia bisa kabur,
you know who will be responsible, right?
kau tahu siapa yang bertanggung jawab, bukan?
Where are you going?
Kau mau ke mana?
To look for Ing.
Mencari Ing.
Why would you do that?
Untuk apa?
She could be anywhere by now.
Dia bisa di mana saja.
She can't follow the rules.
Dia tak bisa mematuhi aturan.
I don't see anyone else having a problem.
Aku tak melihat yang lain bermasalah.
We all want to get out of here, don't we?
Kita semua mau pergi dari sini, bukan?
- Ingkhwan.
- Ingkhwan.
Ingkhwan, where are you?
Ingkhwan, kau di mana?
- Ing. - Can you hear me?
- Ing. - Bisa dengar aku?
- Ingkhwan.
- Ingkhwan.
- Where are you?
- Kau di mana?
- Can you hear me? - Ingkhwan.
- Bisa dengar aku? - Ingkhwan.
- Where are you?
- Kau di mana?
Ingkhwan.
Ingkhwan.
Can you hear me?
Bisa dengar aku?
- Ingkhwan.
- Ingkhwan.
Somebody
Seseorang
help me!
tolong aku!
Ingkhwan, can you hear me?
Ingkhwan, bisa dengar aku?
- Ingkhwan. - Can you hear me?
- Ingkhwan. - Bisa dengar aku?
Help!
Tolong!
Ing…
Ing…
Let me help you.
Biarkan aku membantu.
Let me kill them like always.
Biarkan aku membunuh mereka seperti biasanya
Ing…
Ing…
Ing!
Ing!
Ing.
Ing.
Today, you will all work as usual.
Hari ini, kalian akan bekerja seperti biasa.
No need to look for Ingkhwan.
Tak perlu mencari Ingkhwan.
It's nobody's fault
Yang salah
but the one who chose to break the rules here.
hanya yang memilih untuk melanggar aturan di sini.
If she gets caught,
Jika dia tertangkap,
she'll be severely punished
akan dihukum berat
to set an example.
untuk dijadikan contoh.
You ran off and stayed with Pin?
Kabur lalu bersama Pin?
We looked everywhere for you.
Kami mencarimu ke mana-mana.
It was you girls
Kalian
who threw me in the pit.
melemparku ke lubang.
- What?
- Apa?
It's you
Kaulah
who ran away and are blaming someone else now.
yang kabur lalu kini menyalahkan orang lain.
It's the truth.
Itu benar.
I found her.
Aku menemukan dia.
- You're lying, bumpkin! - Maprang.
- Kau bohong, Kampungan! - Maprang.
You can't follow the rules, so you hid and waited to escape,
Kau tak bisa mengikuti aturan, jadi sembunyi untuk kabur,
- got caught and blaming others! - Quiet!
- tertangkap, dan menyalahkan orang! - Diam!
I don't believe anyone for now.
Belum ada yang kupercayai.
About who is to blame, I'll investigate and punish them later.
Akan kuselidiki siapa yang salah dan kuhukum nanti.
Meanwhile, no more trouble.
Sementara itu, jangan ada lagi masalah.
Go!
Pergi!
Did Maprang really do it?
Maprang sungguh melakukannya?
Was all of this really Maprang's doing?
Apa semua ini sungguh ulah Maprang?
You're so lucky to have made it out alive.
Kau beruntung bisa keluar hidup-hidup.
Ploy.
Ploy.
You've been working with them all along, haven't you?
Selama ini kau bersekongkol dengan mereka, bukan?
I'm sorry.
Maafkan aku.
Do weaklings like us
Apa kaum lemah seperti kita
really have another choice?
sungguh punya pilihan lain?
Cute.
Manis.
Adorable.
Menggemaskan.
Shut up!
Diam!
I said shut up.
Kataku diam.
- Ing!
- Ing!
Hurry up or her parents will find out.
Cepat, nanti orang tuanya tahu.
Ing, where are you?
Ing, kau di mana?
Ing!
Ing!
- Ing.
- Ing.
Ing.
Ing.
Whoever hurt my child,
Siapa pun yang menyakiti anakku,
I will kill them.
akan kubunuh.
Aim.
Aim.
Aim, wake up.
Aim, bangunlah.
Something horrible happened.
Ada kejadian buruk.
What's going on?
Ada apa?
Why did Nuch have to get her?
Kenapa Nuch harus memanggilnya?
Where's Maprang?
Di mana Maprang?
Aim.
Aim.
What happened?
Apa yang terjadi?
Can someone go get Pin to take care of Maprang's body?
Ada yang bisa memanggil Pin untuk mengurus jenazah Maprang?
The godmother ghost did this.
Ini perbuatan hantu ibu baptis.
Ing told me that she's coming for everyone.
Kata Ing, dia akan menyerang semua orang.
It was you, wasn't it?
Kau pelakunya, bukan?
Did you kill my friend?
Kau membunuh temanku?
Aim, enough.
Aim, cukup.
If you think it was me,
Jika menurutmu aku pelakunya,
go ahead and deal with me.
silakan hadapi aku.
Do you dare?
Berani?
Once the storm is over,
Begitu badai reda,
do whatever it takes to get Ingkhwan out of here
usahakan apa pun untuk mengeluarkan Ingkhwan dari sini
and don't come back here again.
dan jangan kembali lagi.
There's a broken radio in the storage behind the school,
Ada radio rusak di gudang belakang sekolah
along with some spare fuel.
dan bahan bakar cadangan.
You may take them all.
Silakan ambil semuanya.
Leave now.
Pergilah sekarang.
And you stay and talk to me.
Kau tetap di sini, bicara denganku.
What happened at Darunphorn?
Apa yang terjadi di Darunphorn?
When people enter the island, Mother always has them bring a newspaper.
Saat orang memasuki pulau, Bunda selalu minta mereka membawa koran.
There may be some news or info about that bumpkin girl.
Mencari berita atau info tentang gadis kampungan itu.
I doubt we'll find anything.
Aku ragu kita akan menemukan apa pun.
Even if we do, I can't read it anyway.
Jika ada pun, tetap tak bisa kubaca.
She must've done some horrible things to end up here.
Pasti dia di sini karena telah berbuat jahat.
My parents died…
Orang tuaku meninggal…
so I was sent there.
jadi aku dikirim ke sana.
I was happy at first…
Awalnya aku senang…
thinking I'd finally have a home like normal kids.
mengira akhirnya akan punya rumah seperti anak lain.
That day,
Pada hari itu,
I woke up
aku bangun
and everyone was just like that.
dan semua orang… sudah begitu.
Girls.
Kawan-Kawan.
TRAGIC MASS KILLING
PEMBUNUHAN MASAL TRAGIS
THIRTY LIVES LOST IN BRUTAL MASSACRE
TIGA PULUH NYAWA MELAYANG DALAM PEMBANTAIAN BRUTAL
SURVIVOR OR KILLER?
PENYINTAS ATAU PEMBUNUH?
THE SOLE SURVIVOR OF THE MASSACRE AT A BOARDING SCHOOL IN LOPBURI
SATU-SATUNYA PENYINTAS PEMBANTAIAN DI ASRAMA DI LOPBURI
I thought I'd get a fresh start here.
Kukira akan dapat awal yang baru di sini.
But here,
Namun, di sini,
there's no difference from before.
sama saja dengan di sana.
Actually…
Sebetulnya…
I learned one thing from everyone here.
ada satu hal yang kupelajari di sini.
The stronger ones always survive.
Yang lebih kuat selalu bertahan.
Retaliate when bullied.
Balaslah saat dirundung.
It would be better if this world were free of those fucking bitches.
Dunia ini akan lebih baik jika bebas dari para jalang sial itu.
Stop it!
Hentikan!
Pack your belongings and get out of here as fast as you can.
Kemasi barang-barangmu dan segera pergi dari sini.
Don't ever let me see your face again.
Jangan sampai aku melihatmu lagi.
Aren't you happy that
Tidakkah kau senang,
some of your horrible students
beberapa siswi jahat
who never learned anything from you
yang tak pernah belajar darimu
finally died?
akhirnya mati?
Pin.
Pin.
I need to talk to you. You got to talk to me.
Aku perlu bicara. Kau harus bicara denganku.
Can't you see I'm carrying this thing?
Tidak lihat aku sedang membawa ini?
Pin, Ing isn't what you think.
Pin, Ing berbeda dari dugaanmu.
Enough, Aim.
Cukup, Aim.
Mother told me to take Ing out of here.
Aku disuruh Bunda membawa Ing.
I won't be coming back.
Aku tak akan kembali.
No, Pin.
Tidak, Pin.
The storm hasn't settled. You can't leave.
Badai belum reda. Jangan pergi.
You can't go with Ing either.
Jangan pergi dengan Ing juga.
Pin, all the bad things that have happened
Pin, semua hal buruk yang telah terjadi
and how Maprang died, it's because of the godmother ghost attached to Ing.
dan kematian Maprang, karena hantu ibu baptis yang bersama Ing.
Stop with the nonsense, Aim.
Hentikan omong kosongmu, Aim.
Are you not admitting it
Kau masih tak mengaku
that all of this was because of you?
bahwa kaulah penyebab semua ini?
Pin, please believe me.
Pin, tolong percaya kepadaku.
Enough, Aim.
Cukup, Aim.
Stop doing horrible things like this.
Berhenti berbuat jahat seperti ini.
All this time, I was a fool.
Selama ini, aku bodoh.
I never knew how horrible you have been to everyone.
Aku baru tahu betapa jahatnya kau ke semua orang.
THREE YEARS EARLIER
TIGA TAHUN SEBELUMNYA
You just got here.
Kau orang baru.
You dare get in trouble?
Sudah berani membuat masalah?
"Aim-orn Amornroj
"Aim-orn Amornroj
sentenced to seven years in juvenile detention
dihukum tujuh tahun di rehabilitasi remaja
for attempted murder of a parent--"
atas percobaan pembunuhan orang tua…"
He isn't my father.
Dia bukan ayahku.
I just didn't allow anyone to oppress me.
Aku cuma tak mau ditekan siapa pun.
If you don't want to stay for too long,
Jika tak mau menetap terlalu lama,
help me keep everyone here in line
bantu aku agar semua tetap mematuhi aturan
and I'll help you gain your freedom.
dan kau akan kubantu mendapatkan kebebasan.
Nuch.
Nuch.
Ploy.
Ploy.
Who's there.
Siapa di sana?
Aim.
Aim.
Pin.
Pin.
You're fine, aren't you?
Kau baik-baik saja, bukan?
We're all fine.
Kami baik-baik saja.
But you…
Namun, kau…
What's wrong?
Ada apa?
The godmother ghost.
Hantu ibu baptis.
She's killing all of us like at that place.
Dia akan membantai kita semua seperti di tempat itu.
But we didn't harm Ing.
Namun, kami tak menyakiti Ing.
The only one who did was…
Yang melakukannya hanya…
DON'T ENTER WITHOUT PERMISSION MOTHER'S ROOM
DILARANG MASUK TANPA IZIN KAMAR BUNDA
SPECIAL ATTENTION NEEDED
BUTUH PERHATIAN KHUSUS
MUST REFORM THEIR ATTITUDE OR THE AUTHORITIES WILL TAKE ACTION.
HARUS MENGUBAH PERILAKU MEREKA ATAU PIHAK BERWAJIB AKAN BERTINDAK.
Aren't you supposed to protect me?
Bukankah kau seharusnya melindungiku?
My mother said whoever hurts me,
Kata ibuku, siapa pun yang menyakitiku,
she will get them.
akan dia bunuh.
You shouldn't kill me.
Kau tak boleh membunuhku.
I'm your Mother.
Aku Bundamu.
I only have one mother.
Aku cuma punya satu ibu.
Mother.
Bunda.
You should see these documents.
Kau sebaiknya melihat dokumen-dokumen ini.
JUVENILE RELEASE ORDER
PERINTAH PEMBEBASAN REMAJA
ORDER TO PARDON JUVENILE OFFENDERS DUE TO THE ONGOING UNREST
PERINTAH MEMBEBASKAN NAPI REMAJA KARENA KERESAHAN YANG TERJADI
THE GOV FORESEES A THREAT FROM COMMUNIST INSURGENTS IN THAILAND
PEMERINTAH MELIHAT ANCAMAN PEMBERONTAK KOMUNIS DI THAILAND
GRANTS AMNESTY TO CONVICTED JUVENILES
MEMBERIKAN AMNESTI KEPADA NAPI REMAJA
AND ASSIGNS THEM TO NATIONAL COMMUNITY SERVICE IMMEDIATELY
DAN SEGERA MENUGASKAN MEREKA UNTUK PELAYANAN PUBLIK NASIONAL
ALL JUVENILES LISTED IN THE ATTACHMENT ARE TO BE RELEASED
SEMUA REMAJA YANG TERDAFTAR DI DOKUMEN LAMPIRAN HARUS DIBEBASKAN
MISS PLOYMONT WONGKUM
PLOYMONT WONGKUM
MISS JINTANUCH WISUTHICHOKE
JINTANUCH WISUTHICHOKE
MISS PRANGTHIP MEEKATE
PRANGTHIP MEEKATE
MISS SAKULTALA NAMUANG
SAKULTALA NAMUANG
MISS AIM-ORN AMORNROJ
AIM-ORN AMORNROJ
What does it say?
Apa isinya?
Many of us have been granted amnesty.
Banyak dari kita yang sudah diberi amnesti.
Why didn't Mother let us go?
Kenapa Bunda tak membebaskan kita?
She's more obsessed with this place than our lives.
Dia lebih terobsesi dengan tempat ini daripada hidup kita.
And
Lalu
what are we going to do?
kita akan berbuat apa?
Testing.
Tes.
Kill them.
Bunuh mereka.
Let me kill them.
Biarkan aku membunuh mereka.
All of them.
Semuanya.
Ing.
Ing.
They hurt me again, Pin.
Mereka menyakitiku lagi, Pin.
Just break its neck, right?
Patahkan saja kepalanya?
What if it doesn't work?
Bagaimana jika tidak bisa?
Dry yourself and clean up the blood first.
Keringkan dirimu dan bersihkan dahulu darahnya.
- Aim. - Pin.
- Aim. - Pin.
Do you believe me now?
Sekarang percaya kepadaku?
What about Mother?
Bagaimana dengan Bunda?
We're the only ones left on the island.
Cuma kita yang tersisa di pulau ini.
Where is Ing? Did she come see you?
Di mana Ing? Apa dia mendatangimu?
I locked her up in the lighthouse.
Dia kukurung di mercusuar.
Don't worry.
Jangan khawatir.
Where are you going?
Kau mau ke mana?
Ing.
Ing.
Pin.
Pin.
Why did you lock me up?
Kenapa mengurungku?
Are you with this horrible bitch now?
Apa kau bersama jalang jahat ini sekarang?
Ing.
Ing.
- Please stop. - They tried to kill me, Pin.
- Hentikan. - Mereka mau membunuhku, Pin.
Did you forget?
Apa kau lupa?
You killed Maprang and Mother.
Kau membunuh Maprang dan Bunda.
Shut up!
Diam!
Ing.
Ing.
Am I that horrible?
Apa aku sejahat itu?
When this bitch did horrible things,
Saat jalang ini berbuat jahat,
nobody gave a shit.
tak ada yang peduli.
All of you
Kalian semua
deserve to die just like those two.
pantas mati seperti mereka berdua.
Ing.
Ing.
What will you get out of this?
Kau akan dapat apa dari ini?
Don't you want a fresh start?
Bukankah kau mau hidup baru?
Aim, just hide in the house.
Aim, sembunyi saja di rumah.
What about you?
Bagaimana denganmu?
Don't worry.
Jangan khawatir.
I'll follow soon.
Aku akan segera menyusul.
Ploy.
Ploy.
Aim.
Aim.
I'm scared.
Aku takut.
What about the others?
Yang lain bagaimana?
Pin.
Pin.
Be quiet.
Jangan berisik.
What did you do?
Kau berbuat apa?
Aim, open the door for me.
Aim, buka pintunya.
Aim.
Aim.
You like it, don't you?
Kau suka, bukan?
Frightening people?
Membuat orang takut?
How does it feel when the tables are turned?
Bagaimana rasanya saat keadaannya berbalik?
Ing.
Ing.
Please don't hurt me.
Kumohon jangan sakiti aku.
We both were bullied by Aim, weren't we?
Kita sama-sama dirundung Aim, bukan?
I've been helping you, remember?
Aku selalu membantumu, ingat?
Get off of me!
Lepaskan aku!
Let go of my child!
Lepaskan anakku!
Aim.
Aim.
Are you okay?
Kau baik-baik saja?
Enough, Ing.
Cukup, Ing.
Fine.
Baiklah.
Let's die together.
Kita mati bersama-sama.
Pin.
Pin.
No one can help you now.
Kini tak ada yang bisa membantu.
Are you happy
Apa kau senang
killing everyone like at that place?
membantai seperti di sana?
Back there,
Di sana,
I didn't mean to.
aku tak sengaja.
But here,
Namun, di sini,
with you…
denganmu…
Where are you going?
Kau mau ke mana?
It won't be over till you're dead.
Ini tak akan usai sampai kau mati.
Let me go!
Lepaskan aku!
Go on. Just kill me.
Ayo. Bunuh saja aku.
I have nowhere to go anyway.
Lagi pula, aku tak punya tempat.
Dying with you doesn't sound so bad.
Mati bersamamu tak terlalu buruk.
Kill me.
Bunuh aku.
You're good at this anyway.
Kau ahli melakukan ini, bukan?
No.
Tidak.
I won't kill you.
Aku tak mau.
I'm about to start my new life
Aku akan memiliki hidup baru
and have a future.
dan masa depan.
Look at you now.
Lihat dirimu sekarang.
Even if you make it out alive,
Walau kau berhasil selamat,
you'll rot in prison anyway.
tetap akan membusuk di penjara.
It's your choice how you want to die.
Kau boleh memilih bagaimana kau akan mati.
No.
Tidak.
Come back and kill me.
Kembalilah dan bunuh aku.
Come back and kill me!
Kembalilah dan bunuh aku!
Do you know
Apa kau tahu
all this time,
selama ini,
how hard I've tried
betapa kerasnya aku berusaha
to stop my mother from killing you all?
menghentikan pembantaian ibuku?
You can't escape what you did.
Kau tak bisa lari dari perbuatanmu.
Come back to me, my child.
Kembalilah kepadaku, Anakku.
I won't let you feel the pain again.
Aku tak akan membiarkanmu merasakan sakit lagi.
Rampa Island.
Pulau Rumpa.
From the Chonburi Fleet Operations Center 527, over.
Dari Pusat Operasi Armada Chonburi 527, ganti.
Upon inspecting the school grounds,
Setelah menginspeksi wilayah sekolah,
we've found the bodies of an adult woman and two young girls.
kami menemukan jasad seorang wanita dewasa dan dua gadis muda.
The bodies show injuries caused by sharp objects.
Jasad menunjukkan luka akibat benda tajam.
I didn't do it.
Bukan aku pelakunya.
It was Ingkhwan and her godmother ghost.
Ingkhwan dan hantu ibu baptisnya.
I'm telling the truth.
Aku berkata jujur.
It wasn't me.
Bukan aku pelakunya.
It was Ingkhwan and her godmother ghost.
Melainkan Ingkhwan dan hantu ibu baptisnya.
Taking the first group of girls out now.
Membawa grup pertama para gadis.
Be careful. Go, go. Let's go.
Hati-hati. Ayo. Jalan.
Ploy.
Ploy.
They're misunderstanding me.
Mereka salah paham terhadapku.
Can you tell them what really happened?
Bisa beri tahu kejadian sebenarnya?
Can you all tell them what happened?
Kalian bisa beri tahu mereka kejadiannya?
Tell them now.
Beri tahu mereka sekarang.
I really didn't do it.
Sungguh bukan aku pelakunya.
Anyone named Ingkhwan here? Has anyone seen her?
Ada yang bernama Ingkhwan di sini? Ada yang melihatnya?
Ploy, tell them.
Ploy, beri tahu mereka.
Tell them what happened.
Beri tahu mereka kejadiannya.
Tell them what Ing did.
Beri tahu mereka perbuatan Ing.
I saved your life.
Aku menyelamatkan nyawamu.
You have to tell them!
Kau harus beri tahu mereka!
Here,
Di sini,
there was no one named Ingkhwan.
tak ada yang bernama Ingkhwan.
The one who did all this is her.
Ini semua perbuatannya.
We all can back that up.
Kami semua bisa bersaksi.
I've been waiting for this day.
Hari ini sudah kunantikan.
The day you have to pay.
Hari saat kau harus membayar.
Just kill her, Ing.
Bunuh saja dia, Ing.
I won't tell anyone about this.
Aku tak akan memberi tahu siapa pun.
What did you just say?
Apa katamu?
- Calm down, kid. - You said I did it?
- Tenanglah, Nak. - Katamu aku pelakunya?
You said I did it?
Katamu aku pelakunya?
Calm down.
Tenanglah.
I saved your life! And yours! You should remember that!
Aku menyelamatkan nyawamu! Kalian juga! Kalian harus ingat itu!
That's enough. Let's go.
Cukup. Ayo pergi.
- Let me go. I didn't do it. - Let's go.
- Lepaskan aku. Bukan aku pelakunya. - Ayo.
- I didn't do it.
- Bukan aku pelakunya. - Ayo pergi.
Mother always said that
Bunda selalu bilang
this place provides everyone
tempat ini memberi semua orang
a fresh start with hope,
awal yang baru dengan harapan,
only if you listen and follow the rules.
asalkan kau mendengar dan mematuhi aturan.
PINITKHUN, REMEMBER AND UPHOLD OUR TEACHER'S WORDS
PINITKHUN, INGATLAH DAN JUNJUNGLAH KATA-KATA GURU KITA
But I don't buy that crap
Namun, aku tak memercayai omong kosong itu.
because every rule in this world is rigged.
Setiap aturan di dunia ini curang.
It's there to protect powerful people.
Ada untuk melindungi yang berkuasa.
People like us still have to fight each other
Orang seperti kita masih harus saling bersaing
just to barely survive another day.
cuma untuk bertahan satu hari lagi.
Right, Ing?
Benar, Ing?